Finding Aid for Theodore J. St. Antoine Papers 1966-1993
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Theodore J. St. Antoine Papers 1966-1993
St. Antoine, Theodore J.
14 linear feet
Theodore St. Antoine, currently James E. and Sarah A. Degan Professor Emeritus of Law, has been an acknowledged expert in labor relations law since the late 1960s, and is a practicing labor arbitrator. He has also distinguished himself with a full service record, participating in and leading numerous committees, councils and other organizations in the labor law field as well as at the University of Michigan, including guiding the Law School as Dean from 1971 through 1978. The papers document the academic and public service aspects of St. Antoine's law career, from 1966 through 1993. The files are divided into four series: Arbitration Case Files; Articles, Speeches, Appearances and Conferences; Correspondence; and Public Service/Committee Work.
0116 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Materials were received with School (Donor 343 ) records in 1988 and 1999
The collection is open for research.
Theodore St. Antoine, currently James E. and Sarah A. Degan Professor Emeritus of Law, has been an acknowledged expert in labor relations law since the late 1960s, and is a practicing labor arbitrator. He has also distinguished himself with a full service record, participating in and leading numerous committees, councils and other organizations in the labor law field as well as at the University of Michigan, including guiding the Law School as Dean from 1971 through 1978. He is married to Elizabeth Lloyd (Frier), and they have four children.
Theodore St. Antoine was born in Vermont on May 29, 1929. He graduated from Fordham University in 1951 with a degree in philosophy and theology, and from the University of Michigan Law School in 1954, having served as editor-in-chief of the Michigan Law Review. He did post-graduate work with a Fulbright Grant at the London School of Economics, and on his return to the United States, he practiced in Cleveland and the U.S. Army, and then in Washington D.C. with the firm Woll, Mayer and St. Antoine. In 1965, after seven years in D.C., he joined the University of Michigan Law School faculty, teaching courses in contracts, and labor and employment law.
As Dean of the Law School from 1971 through 1978, he raised the funds for the underground law library addition, and saw it through the ground-breaking in 1978. His wisdom and even-handedness, and his flawless negotiating skills, are celebrated in his roles as both teacher and administrator. His students for years have called him "The Saint."
Though limited by university policy to ten to fifteen cases a year, St. Antoine also practices labor arbitration through the Michigan Employment Relations Bureau, the National Arbitrators Academy (NAA), and the American Arbitration Association. Several of his opinions have been published, and he is often cited in other arbitrators' decisions. He participates in an executive capacity in arbitration societies, and served as president of the NAA during the 1999/2000 term.
St. Antoine's other public service activities include both university-related and outside work. He was presented with a Distinguished Faculty Governance Award in 1996 in recognition of his service at the university, beginning in the 1970s as chair of the University Council and as a member of the Ad Hoc Committee on a Permanent Judiciary, then as President of the Research Club in 1989-1990, and as chair of the Faculty Senate's Academic Affairs Advisory Committee, among other positions.
Outside of the university, St. Antoine has served as Secretary and Council member for the Labor and Employment Law Section of the American Bar Association, as chair of the Labor Law Section of the Michigan State Bar, and as chair of the UAW-GM Legal Services Plan. In January of 2000, he received the Distinguished Service Award from the Labor and Employment Law Section of the State Bar of Michigan. He was the reporter, or principal draftsman, of the Model Employment Termination Act for the National Conference of Commissioners on Uniform State Law (NCCUSL), which he worked on from 1987 through 1992. The NCCUSL passed the model act in 1992, despite much initial contention, but it was not widely adopted.
St. Antoine is currently a member of the UAW's Public Review Board, and a member of the U.S. Executive Board of the International Society for Labor Law and Social Security. His casebook, Labor Relations Law, is in its tenth edition.
The papers document the academic and public service aspects of St. Antoine's law career, from 1966 through 1993. The files are divided into four series: Arbitration Case Files; Articles, Speeches, Appearances and Conferences; Correspondence; and Public Service/Committee Work. The series reflect the original order of the materials.
Subjects:
St. Antoine, Theodore J., 1929-; University of Michigan--Law School--Faculty.; UAW-GM Legal Services Plan.; Workers' compensation--Law and legislation--Michigan.; Labor laws and legislation--Michigan.; Arbitration, Industrial.; Lawyers--Michigan.
- Arbitration Case Files
  The Arbitration Case Files contain a non-random sample of a twenty-five linear foot series in the original accession. The files selected document the arbitration cases which were published, thus ensuring that the parties do not expect the complete confidentiality of the record of the arbitration proceedings. There are three cases represented here: a 1970 case between the City of Birmingham (Michigan) and the City of Birmingham Firefighters, a 1985 grievance by UFCW (United Food and Commercial Workers) Local 876 against Kroger, and the Wayne State Chapter of the American Association of University Professors (AAUP) grievance against Wayne State University in 1975.
  - City of Birmingham and City of Birmingham Firefighters 1970 (Box 1)
    In the Birmingham Firefighters proceedings, St. Antoine arbitrated the reasonable settlement of disputes about the new contract between the firefighters and the city. The primary contentious issues were whether or not to institute an agency shop, and whether arbitration should be the final recourse for the resolution of grievances (rather than the city commission, which was assumed to have an obvious bias.) In St. Antoine's decision, he found the agency shop unnecessary, but instituted the final arbitration clause.
  - Kroger and UFCW Local 876 1985 (Box 1)
    The grievance of UFCW Local 876 against Kroger was that the labor contract mandated the store be closed on New Years' Day, yet Kroger remained open in 1985 in response to the same action by competitors, which the company claimed was contractually allowed. St. Antoine found for the union.
  - Wayne State University and Wayne State Chapter, American Association of University Professors 1975 (Box 1)
    The AAUP case concerned a member of the Wayne State University faculty who was denied tenure. The grievant claimed that his tenure was guaranteed him when he was hired by the university. St. Antoine found for the university.
- Articles, Speeches, Appearances and Conferences
  The series Articles, Speeches, Appearances and Conferences contains files of St. Antoine's writings and conference correspondence from two accessions--one from 1988, (the bulk of this accession otherwise remains in the Law School record group, and pertains to St. Antoine's duties as dean), and one from 1999. The earlier accession contains files for the years 1967 through 1978, and are arranged chronologically. The files from the 1999 accession were split into two groups--By Title or Subject and By Conference or Venue. All of the writings found here were the result of St. Antoine's participation in conferences, or appearance at other functions, though not all of the files of the various conferences contain any writings. The writings are represented variously by rough notes, outlines, typed manuscripts, or published proceedings or law review reprints.
  - 1967
    - Michigan State Bar Association Labor Relations Law Section--"The Labor Board and the Arbitrators," May 28 (Box 2)
  - 1970
    - "The Consent of the Governed--Public Employee Unions and the Law," 1970 (Box 2)
    - "Interventionism, Laissez-Faire, and Stare Decisis: The Labor Decisions of the Supreme Court, October 1969," 1970 (Box 2)
    - "Secondary Boycott: From Antitrust to Labor Relations," 1970 (Box 2)
  - 1971
    - Washtenaw County Bar--"The Law School in the 70s," February 24 (Box 2)
    - State Bar of California, San Francisco, September 16 (Box 2)
    - Institute of Continuing Legal Education--Faculty Power; Collective Bargaining, September 17 (Box 2)
    - Police and the Courts, Ann Arbor, September 24 (Box 2)
    - Chicago Alumni Luncheon, October 12 (Box 2)
    - Seventh Annual Labor Relations Institute--"Interventionism, Laissez-Faire, and Stare Decisis: The Labor Decisions of the Supreme Court, October Term 1969," Atlanta, October 21 (Box 2)
  - 1972
    - ABA Section of Labor Relations Law, Mexico City, January 21 (Box 2)
    - Albion College, March 11 (Box 2)
    - Fordham University, Alumni Association Dinner, April 7 (Box 2)
    - Kansas City, Missouri Alumni, April 20 (Box 2)
    - Dearborn Bar Association, April 27 (Box 2)
    - Law Day, Benton Harbor--"Law, Order and the Consent of the Governed," May 1 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1917 Reunion (includes photograph), May 5 (Box 2)
    - American Bar Association Section of Labor Relations Law--"Judicial Caution and the Supreme Court's Labor Decisions, October Term 1971," August 14 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1942 Reunion, October 28 (Box 2)
    - Association of American Law Schools, New York, December 30 (Box 2)
  - 1973
    - Great Lakes Assembly, March 31 (Box 2)
    - ABA Section Labor Relations Law, Washington D.C., August 7 (Box 2)
    - California State Bar Meeting, September 12 (Box 2)
    - Committee on Institutional Cooperation Meeting, September 19 (Box 2)
    - AFL-CIO Lawyers Conference, Miami, Florida, October 22 (Box 2)
    - Law School Deans--Multi-State Bar Examination, November, 2 (Box 2)
  - 1974
    - American Bar Association, Honolulu, August 15 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1954 Reunion, September 27 (Box 2)
    - University of Wisconsin--ABA/AALS Report December 1974-September 1975 (Box 2)
  - 1975
    - Pacific Coast Labor Law Conference--"Major Labor Law Developments May 1974-April 1975 Fresh Perspectives on Familiar Terrain," May 8 (Box 2)
    - Trip to Japan/Philippines (includes photographs), May 18 (Box 2)
    - Workmen's Compensation, June 6 (Box 2)
    - UAW Public Review Board, Detroit Airport, June 21 (Box 2)
    - Columbus Bar Association, September 17 (Box 2)
    - Catholics in America, Wayne State, October 22 (Box 2)
    - Rutgers Law School Symposium--"Affirmative Action: Hypocritical Euphemism or Noble Mandate?," November 28 (Box 2)
  - 1976
    - University of Virginia Symposium--"Connell: Antitrust Law at the Expense of Labor Law," January (Box 2)
    - Michigan Municipal League, Ann Arbor, January 9 (Box 2)
    - New York Alumni, January 30 (Box 2)
    - Institute of Continuing Legal Education Labor Law and Practice, Dearborn, February 13 (Box 2)
    - Judicial Qualifications Committee, April 1 (Box 2)
    - Jackson, Michigan Seminar, June 12 (Box 2)
    - National Association of Law Placement, June 16 (Box 2)
    - American Bar Association (includes photograph), June 25 (Box 2)
    - Council on Legal Education for Professional Responsibility, November 18-19 (Box 2)
    - Institute of Continuing Legal Education, December 2 (Box 2)
    - American Association of Law Schools--"How the Law Schools can Justify an Increasing Share of a Decreasing Pie," December 27-30 (Box 2)
  - 1977
    - American Bar Association Dean's Workshop, February 9 (Box 2)
    - International Union of Electrical Workers, May 23 (Box 2)
    - American Bar Association Program Committee, August 7 (Box 2)
    - House Labor-Management Subcommittee, September 7 (Box 2)
    - Industrial Relations Research Association--"Proposed Labor Reform: 'Brave New World' or 'Looking Backward,'" December 29 (Box 2)
  - 1978
    - Committee on Judicial Qualifications
      - March 28 (Box 2)
      - April 3 (Box 2)
      - April 9 (Box 2)
      - April 19 (Box 2)
      - April 22, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - American Law Institute, May 16-19 (Box 3)
    - Third Annual Conference of Prepaid Legal Services, June 15-16 (Box 3)
  - 1979-1993
    - By Title or Subject
      - Affirmative Action and Title VII--Federalist Society Debate with Richard Epstein 1992-1993 (Box 3)
      - Arab-Israeli Debate (moderator)--Uriel Savir and Nabeel Abraham 1992 (Box 3)
      - "At Will Employment and the Handsome American"--University of California at Los Angeles Ben Aaron Lecture 1987-1989 (Box 3)
      - "At Will Employment: An Overview"--American Bar Association Annual Meeting/Michigan State University U.S. Labor and Employment Policy Meeting 1988 (Box 3)
      - "Binding Arbitration--Role of Law and Policy"--Society of Professionals in Dispute Resolution 1989-1990 (Box 3)
      - "Celebrating the 75th Anniversary of the Federal Employees' Compensation Act"--Rutgers University Institute of Management and Labor Relations Symposium 1991 (Box 3)
      - "The Collective Bargaining Process"
        - The Labor Board at Mid-Century Symposium in American Labor Policy: A Critical Appraisal of the National Labor Relations Act, 1987 (Box 3)
        - University of Natal (S. Africa) Centre for Socio-Legal Studies Seminar 1988-1989 (Box 3)
      - "Commentary on Leslie's 'Multiemployer Bargaining Rules:' The Limitations of a Strictly Economic Analysis"--University of Virginia Conference on Law and Economics of Bargaining 1988-1989 (Box 3)
      - "Comparable Worth: What it is and Its Status Today"--Michigan Civil Service Commission Comparable Worth Task Force 1983-1985 (Box 3)
      - "Deferral to Arbitration and Use of External Law in Arbitration"--Southern California Labor Law Symposium 1987 (Box 3)
      - "The Duty to Bargain in the Era of World Markets, 'Givebacks' and Participative Management"--Labor and Employment Law in the U.S. Conference (Tampa, FL) 1986 (Box 3)
      - "Employment at Will: The Evolving State of the Law"--Southern Methodist University School of Law 1985 (Box 3)
      - Employment Discrimination--Florida Institute of Legal Studies 1979 (Box 3)
      - Employment Termination Act
        - American Arbitration Association Rocky Mountain Employment Issues Conference 1990 (Box 3)
        - Atlanta Bar Section 1989-1991 (Box 3)
        - "The Model Employment Termination Act--A Feasible Compromise of Competing Worthy Interests"
          - California State Bar Labor and Employment Law Section Conference 1992 (Box 3)
          - St. Louis University Center for Employment Law 1992 (Box 3)
        - Minnesota Bar Labor Section/Philadelphia Industrial Relations Research Association 1989 (Box 3)
        - Minnesota Employment Law Council 1990-1991 (Box 3)
        - New York University Conference on Labor 1992-1993 (Box 3)
        - Seattle-King County Bar Association 1992 (Box 3)
        - University of Michigan Law Alumni--Chicago 1991 (Box 3)
      - Globalization of U.S. Industry--Detroit College of Law 1986 (Box 3)
      - "Hiring and Firing: The New Rules" Conference--Bureau of National Affairs, Inc. 1988 (Box 3)
      - Journal of Individual Employment Rights ("Foreword"), 1991-1992 (Box 3)
      - Journal of Law Reform ("Introduction"), 1985-1986 (Box 3)
      - Justice System Advisory Committee for Caseflow Management (Washtenaw County) 1992 (Box 3)
      - The Labor Law Curriculum of the Future--Association of American Law Schools 1984-1985 (Box 3)
      - "Labor" / "Picketing"/ "Boycotts"--in the Encyclopedia of the American Constitution, 1982-1991 (Box 3)
      - "The Legal and Economic Implications of Union-Management Cooperation: The Case of General Motors and the United Auto Workers"--New York University Labor Conference 1988-1989 (Box 3)
      - "The Legal Framework of Labor Arbitration in the Private Sector"--American Bar Association Labor Arbitration Advocacy Program 1987-1989 (Box 3)
      - "Legal Implications of Quality of Work Life Programs"--Oakland University Labor Studies Center 1987 (Box 3)
      - "Major Labor and Employment Decisions of the Supreme Court 1988-1989 Term"--Southwestern Labor Law Conference, 1989 (Box 3)
      - Leroy Merrifield Tribute-- George Washington University Law Review, 1986-1987 (Box 3)
      - Minority and Women Labor Arbitrator Development Program--American Arbitration Association 1987 (Box 3)
      - "The Modification of Employment at Will Enters a New Phase"--Association of American Law Schools Annual Meeting 1987 (Box 3)
      - Oversight of Government Management, U.S. Senate Subcommittee on 1986 (Box 4)
      - William Pierce Tribute-- Michigan Law Review, 1991 (Box 4)
      - "Presenting an Interest Arbitration"--American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO) Arbitration Workshop 1988 (Box 4)
      - "Race, Sex and Age Discrimination Update"--Los Angeles County Bar Association/Institute for Continuing Legal Education Labor Law Seminar 1985 (Box 4)
      - "Recent Labor Law Decisions of the Supreme Court"--Illinois Institute for Continuing Legal Education Employment Relations Conference 1983-1984 (Box 4)
      - John Reed Tribute-- Michigan Law Review, 1987-1989 (Box 4)
      - "Requiring 'Just Cause' for Discharges: Modifications in At-Will Employment"--American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO) Lawyers Conference 1982 (Box 4)
      - Review-- A Guide to Critical Legal Studies by Mark Kelman-- Cornell University Industrial and Labor Relations Review, 1989 (Box 4)
      - "The Revision of Employment at Will Enters a New Phase"--Industrial Relations Research Association/Association of General Counsel of Hawaii 1985-1986 (Box 4)
      - "Rights and Remedies Under Title VII of the Civil Rights Act and the Age Discrimination in Employment Act"--Fitness to Work Conference 1991 (Box 4)
      - Rights in the Workplace Conference--American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) 1990 (Box 4)
      - "A Seed Germinates: Unjust Discharge Reform Heads Toward Full Flower"-- Nebraska Law Review, 1987-1989 (Box 4)
      - Strategic Collective Bargaining Workshop--University of Michigan Business School 1987-1990 (Box 4)
      - Union Democracy Symposium (Introduction)-- University of Michigan Journal of Law Reform, 1991 (Box 4)
      - "What Corporate Counsel Must Understand About Recent Supreme Court Labor Law Decisions and the Model Employment Termination Act"--Illinois Institute of Continuing Legal Education 1991 (Box 4)
      - "Wrongful Discharge Law--Perspectives and Prognosis"--American Bar Association National Institute on Litigating Wrongful Discharge and Invasion of Privacy Claims 1986 (Box 4)
      - "Wrongful Discharge--Uniform Employment Termination Act"--Iowa Association of Business and Industry, Lake Okoboji, IA 1990 (Box 4)
    - By Conference or Venue
      - Chicago-Kent Arbitration Symposium ("Afterward") 1989-1992 (Box 4)
      - Commerce Clearing House Labor Advisor Panel 1986-1992 (Box 4)
      - Federal Bar Association Labor Law Seminar 1988 (Box 4)
      - Institute for Continuing Legal Education (ICLE) Advocacy Institute 1987 (Box 4)
      - London Alumni Meeting February 1991 (Box 4)
      - Michigan Employment Relations Commission 1988-1993 (Box 4)
      - Michigan Law School Club of Washington DC (Speech to Alumni) 1992-1993 (Box 4)
      - Michigan Press--Reviewing 1989-1991 (Box 4)
      - The Labor Law Group 1984 (Box 4)
      - National Practice Institute--Labor Arbitration Conference 1988-1991 (Box 4)
      - Pacific Coast Labor Law Conference April 1989 (Box 4)
      - Public Employment Relations Act Conference 1990 (Box 4)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence is arranged roughly alphabetically. Covering the years 1972 to 1993, the correspondence is both incoming and outgoing. It documents his career both outside and inside the Law School, including communication with students and colleagues, as well as some personal materials.
  - A-B 1978-1993, undated, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - C-D 1972-1993, undated, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - F-G 1978-1992, undated, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - H 1970-1991, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - I-L
    - 1976-1986, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1987-1992 undated (Box 6)
  - M-Mc 1978-1992, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - N-R 1978-1992, 5 folders (Box 6)
  - S 1978-1992, undated, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - T 1980-1991, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - V-Z 1980-1991, 4 folders (Box 6)
- Public Service/Committee Work
  The largest series is Public Service/Committee Work, and contains the files of some of St. Antoine's most important and well-known work. Found here is documentation of his participation in American Bar Association and Michigan State Bar Association committees, of his (donated) time as Michigan Governor's (James Blanchard) Special Counselor on Workers' Compensation, and of his chairmanship of the UAW-GM Legal Services Plan, for example. These files often contain correspondence, research notes, memoranda, and reports.
  - Affirmative Action Committee 1987-1988 (Box 7)
  - American Association of Law Schools
    - Committee on Admissions to the Bar 1977-1982, 5 folders (Box 7)
  - American Bar Association
    - Associate and Advisory Committee to the Standing Committee on Continuing Education 1973 (Box 7)
    - Committee on Individual Rights and Responsibilities
      - Annual Meetings 1983-1984, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Correspondence 1981-1984, 6 folders (Box 7)
      - Report circa 1984 (Box 7)
    - Labor Law Section Public Advisory Committee 1976-1978 (Box 7)
  - Lobbying Activities 1990-1991 (Box 7)
  - Conflict of Interest Task Force (University of Michigan) 1984-1985 (Box 8)
  - Fordham University Board of Trustees 1984 (Box 8)
  - Fordham Law School--American Bar Association Accreditation 1979-1982 (Box 8)
  - Institute of Labor and Industrial Relations
    - 1981-1983, 1989 (Box 8)
    - Executive Board 1981-1986 (Box 8)
    - The Role of Higher Education in Facilitating Labor-Management Cooperation Conference 1986 (Box 8)
    - Workers' Basic Study Program 1966 (Box 8)
  - Jacobs, Francis--1993 DeRoy Fellow 1993 (Box 8)
  - Michigan Civil Service Commission--Advisory Employment Relations Committee
    - "Report and Recommendations on Unit Determination and Representation in the State Classified Civil Service," 1974 (Box 8)
  - The Michigan Committee (University of Michigan) 1981 (Box 8)
  - Michigan Governor's (Milliken) Workmen's Compensation Advisory Committee
    - Correspondence 1974-1975 (Box 8)
    - Report 1975 (Box 8)
  - Michigan Governor's (Blanchard) Special Counselor on Workers' Compensation
    - "Workers' Compensation in Michigan: Costs, Benefits, and Fairness--A Report to Governor James J. Blanchard's Cabinet Council on Jobs and Economic Development from Theodore J. St. Antoine, Special Counselor on Workers' Compensation" (Final Report) December 1984 (Box 8)
    - Volume I
      - Background 1983-1985
        - [Part 1], 4 folders; 13 volumes (Box 8)
        - [Part 2], 21 folders (Box 9)
      - Correspondence 1983-1985, 5 folders (Box 9)
    - Volume II
      - Axelrod, Solomon--Medical Costs Report 1984 (Box 10)
      - Background 1984-1986, 10 folders; 1 volumes
      - Boonin, Robert A.--Research Assistant 1984-1985 (Box 10)
      - Burton, John F
        - Benefits Report 1985 (Box 10)
        - Correspondence 1984 (Box 10)
        - Employers' Costs Report 1985 (Box 10)
      - Contract Between Theodore J. St. Antoine and Bureau of Worker's Disability Compensation 1984 (Box 10)
      - Correspondence 1984-1986 (Box 10)
      - Correspondence--Reactions to Final Report 1985, 2 folders (Box 10)